Guide to the Donald F. Poulson Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Donald F. Poulson papers
1943-1981
MS 1731
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
11
(11 boxes)
The papers are composed of administrative and research files, course materials, and writings, which document Donald F. Poulson's work in the field of developmental genetics and his service on the faculty of Yale University. The papers highlight Poulson's role as first chairman of Yale's Department of Biology.
Poulson, Donald F.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Donald F. Poulson estate, 1997.
Conditions Governing Access
The papers are closed until January 1, 2057, due to the presence of student papers and Yale University administrative records.
Biographical / Historical
Donald F. Poulson, a founder of developmental genetics, earned a Ph.D. from the California Institute of Technology in 1936 for his studies of the embryonic development of Drosophila fruit flies. He joined the Yale faculty in 1937, attained the rank of full professor in 1955, and remained an active researcher there until his retirement in 1981. Poulson was the first chairman of Yale's Department of Biology (1962-1965). He died in 1989.
Scope and Contents
The papers are composed of administrative and research files, course materials, and writings, which document Donald F. Poulson's work in the field of developmental genetics and his service on the faculty of Yale University. The papers highlight Poulson's role as first chairman of Yale's Department of Biology.
Biology; Developmental genetics; Drosophila -- Genetics; Poulson, Donald F.; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Biology Department
- Administrative, research, and teaching files, 1950s-1960s (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  The files include correspondence, research data, course materials and student papers for Zool 37a (Genetics), Zool 45, Zool 50, Zool 127a.
- Administrative and teaching files, 1940s-1970s (Box 2)
  The files include correspondence concerning Calhoun College and Yale College; committee files, including B. S. Course of Study; and course materials and student papers for Zool 45, Biol II, and Sci III.
- Research and teaching files, 1960s-1970s (Box 3)
  The files include correspondence; Poulson reprints; course materials and student papers; and research files and data on EMG, Sex Ratio, D. Nebulosa, and Nebulosa SR.
- Research files and data, 1950s-1960s (Box 4)
  The files concern SR, Sex Ratio.
- Professional (activities), research, and teaching files, 1960s-1980s (Box 5)
  The files include writings; presentations; grant applications and reports; correspondence; and student and faculty recommendations and evaluations.
- Administrative, research, and teaching files, 1960s-1970s (Box 6)
  The files include graduate student thesis advising files; grant applications and reports; and departmental meeting minutes, correspondence, and reports.
- Administrative, professional (activities), and teaching files, 1940s-1970s (Box 7)
  The files include grant applications and reports; grant proposals (for Poulson review); conference files; presentations; and search committee files.
- Administrative, professional (activities), and teaching files, 1950s-1970s (Box 8)
  The files include correspondence, meeting minutes, and reports concerning graduate students; finances; the Executive Committee; course material; Biol II; journal article reviews; and symposia.
- Administrative and professional (activities) files, 1950s-1960s (Box 9)
  The files include correspondence, meeting minutes, and reports concerning facilities; conferences and lectures; George Evelyn Hutchinson; the Petrunkevitch Fund; the Cold Spring Harbor Committee; regulations; faculty publications; Fulbright; and professional societies.
- Administrative files, 1950s-1970s (Box 10)
  The files include correspondence, meeting minutes, and reports concerning faculty evaluations; the National Science Foundation U. S. - Japan Program; lab rules and regulations; a Biology Department brochure; and the Biology Department Executive Committee.
- Exams for courses, 1940s-1960s (Box 11)
  The files include blank exams for Zool 37a (Genetics), Bio 10, Bio 27b, Bio 128, Biophysics, and Cytology.